Connecticut Yankee Atomic Power Company
© 2006 University of Connecticut
Connecticut Yankee Atomic Power Company, Haddam Neck Plant Records.
undated, 1963-2005.
Archives & Special Collections at the Thomas J. Dodd Center.
Connecticut Yankee Atomic Power Company.
190 linear feet.
MSS20060202
Connecticut Yankee Atomic Power Company was a nuclear power plant located in Haddam Neck, Connecticut. It began commercial operation in 1968 and produced over 110 billion kilowatt-hours of electricity in its 29 years of service. In 1996 the CY Board of Directors voted to permanently close the plant and decommissioning was completed in 2007. The records consist of plant design drawings, plant historical records, employee newsletters, environmental reports, regulatory correspondence, scrapbooks, plaques, photographs, and other audiovisual materials.
History
Connecticut Yankee Atomic Power Company was a nuclear power plant located in Haddam Neck, Connecticut. The first commercial nuclear power plant in the state, it began operation on January 1, 1968, with an initial capacity of 490,000 kilowatts. Its capacity was later increased to 582,000 kilowatts. In its twenty-nine years of service the plant produced over 110 billion kilowatt-hours of electricity. The plant was formally retired on December 6, 1996, when the Board of Directors voted to permanently close the plant after an economic analysis determined the cost of supplying electricity was not beneficial to its customers.
Decommissioning of the plant, known as a "construction in reverse" process, began in 1998. Connecticut Yankee chose to dismantle the site, as opposed to placing it in protective storage or sealing it and leaving it in place for decades. The process to decommission a nuclear power plant involves reducing the amount of radioactivity on the site to a level that allows the site to be released for future use. It is a step-by-step process that takes years to complete and involves the decontamination and dismantling of existing facilities, cleanup for any contaminated soil, and possible groundwater treatment.
The dismantling of the plant was monitored by the Nuclear Regulatory Commission and other government agencies as well as local citizen groups. A storage facility was constructed about ¾ mile from the reactor site for dry cask storage of the plant's 1019 spent fuel assemblies. Decommissioning of the plant concluded in 2007.
The decommissioning project required compliance with federal legislation regarding the preservation and management of archaeological sites. From 2002 to 2006, Connecticut Yankee commissioned several archaeologists to undertake reconnaissance surveys to identify and evaluate archaeological resources on the Haddam Neck property.
Scope and Content
The Connecticut Yankee Atomic Power Company, Haddam Neck Plant, Records consist of plant design drawings, plant historical records, employee newsletters, environmental reports, regulatory correspondence, scrapbooks, plaques, photographs, and other audiovisual materials.
Arrangement
The collection is arranged into seven series.
Series I: Plant Design Drawings Set, ( undated )
Series II: Plant Historical Records, ( 1963-1997 )
Series III: Employee Newsletters, ( 1984-2003 )
Series IV: Scrapbooks of newspaper clippings related to Connecticut Yankee, ( 1991-2004 )
Series V: Plaques, ( 1988-1995 )
Series VI: Photographs and display boards, ( 1966-2003 )
Series VII: Other Audiovisual materials, ( 1966-2004 )
Series VIII: 2007 addition, ( 1966-2005 )
Related Material
Archives & Special Collections has a substantial collection of materials pertaining to Connecticut business records. For detailed information on these collections please contact the curator or ask at the reference desk.
Index Terms
This record series is indexed under the following controlled access subject terms.
Organizations:
Connecticut Yankee Atomic Power Company.
Places:
Haddam Neck (Conn.)
Subjects:
Nuclear power plants -- Connecticut.; Nuclear power plants -- Decommissioning.
Document Types:
Correspondence.; Notebooks.; Publications.; Photographs.; Blueprints.; Maps.; Administrative Records.; Financial Records.; Minutes.; Press releases.; Videocassettes.; Audio cassettes.; Audio visual materials.; Fliers. [printed matter]; Photocopies.; Notes.; Motion picture film.; Scrap-Books.; Newsletters.; Newspapers.; Microfilm.; Filmstrips.; Histories.
Restrictions on Access
There are no access restrictions on this collection.
Acquisition Information
The Connecticut Yankee Atomic Power Company Records were donated by the company in March 2006.
Detailed Description
- Series I: Plant Design Drawings Set, undated
  - Plant Design Drawings (punch cards with microform), undated (Box 1-2)
- Series II: Plant Historical Records, 1963-2004
  - Subseries A: Regulatory affairs correspondence, 1963-1997 (Box 3-33)
  - Subseries B: General employee information files, including files for employee safety and emergency preparedness; newspaper clippings and press releases about Connecticut Yankee, "Dear Neighbor" letters (to residents of Haddam Neck, Connecticut); 1997 improvement plan for employee performance issues (to improve efficiency), Connecticut River ecological studies (1990-2000s); [note that there is no information about individual employees], 1965-2004 (Box 34-35)
  - Subseries C: Citizens Decommissioning Advisory Committee materials (boxes 36 and 37 consist of VHS tapes and audio cassettes of meetings with citizen groups), 1997-2004 (Box 36-38)
  - Subseries D: Plant Log books, 1980-1990, 2000-2002 (Box 39-41)
  - Subseries E: Technical manuals, 1971-2004 (Box 42-57)
  - Subseries F: Incident report books, 1964-2003 (Box 58-62)
  - Subseries G: Technical reports and documents, 1964-1999 (Box 63-67)
- Series III: Employee newsletters, 1984-2003
  - Subseries A: CY Today, 1995-2003 (Box 68-69)
  - Subseries B: Predecessor newsletters, 1984-1994 (Box 70)
- Series IV: Scrapbooks of newspaper clippings related to Connecticut Yankee, 1991-2004
  - Scrapbooks, 1991-2004 (Box 71-81)
- Series V: Plaques, 1988-1995
  - Plaques, 1988-1995 (Box 82-83)
- Series VI: Photographs and display boards, 1966-2003
  - Photographs and display boards, 1966-2003 (Box 84-112, 116-128)
- Series VII: Other Audiovisual materials, 1966-2004
  - Subseries A: Videotapes, 1966-2004 (Box 113-115)
  - Subseries B: Film, 1969-1977 (Box Unboxed)
- Series VIII: 2007 addition, undated, 1966-2005
  - Quality Assurance memos, logs, surveillance reports, undated (Box 129)
  - Letters and memos for RCRA and Groundwater studies, 2002-2004 (Box 130)
  - Plant design, discharge canal dredging, 1967 (Box 131)
  - Original operating license, Connecticut River study, 1967 (Box 132)
  - Groundwater reports, environmental report, 1966, 2003 (Box 133)
  - Decommissioning environmental review, groundwater report, plant design basis books, 1989, 1999 (Box 134)
  - Plant design basis books, 1989 (Box 135)
  - Decomissioning photographs, undated (Box 136)
  - Slides of plant operations and refueling, undated (Box 137)
  - Canal dredging permits, 2003 (Box 138)
  - Site characterization reports, 2004 (Box 139)
  - Dredging and demolition permits, 2004-2005 (Box 140)
  - Groundwater characterization report, 2004 (Box 141)
  - PCB Paint removal permit, Limited field investigation reports, 2002 (Box 142)
  - Ecorisk study, Plant Safety Assessment, 1983, 2004 (Box 143)
  - Aquatic Resources study, 2003 (Box 144)
  - Groundwater report, Ecorisk reports, 2005 (Box 145)
  - Videotapes and CDs, undated (Box 146)
  - Photographs and videotapes, undated (Box 147)
  - Photographs, undated (Box 148)
  - NAC STS Safety analysis report, undated (Box 149)
  - License termination plan, undated (Box 150)
  - NAC MPC Safety analysis report, undated (Box 151)
  - Phase 2 Final status survey (FSS) reports, undated (Box 152)
  - Design document reports, undated (Box 153)
  - Early site characterization documents, undated (Box 154)
  - License extension, 1974 (Box 155)
  - Phase 4 FSS reports, undated (Box 156)
  - Phase 2 FSS reports, undated (Box 157)
  - Regulatory correspondence logs, undated (Box 158)
  - Log books and regulatory affairs memos, 2005 (Box 159)
  - Site characterization reports, undated (Box 160)
  - Regulatory correspondence, 2001 (Box 161)
  - Videotapes, canal dredging application, undated (Box 162)
  - Regulatory affairs memos and logs, undated (Box 163)
  - Site characterization reports, undated (Box 164)
  - Integrated site closure plan, DEP permits, undated (Box 165)
  - Early environmental reports, undated (Box 166)
  - Regulatory correspondence, 2000 (Box 167-172)
  - Early environmental reports, undated (Box 173)
  - Memos, 2002 (Box 174)
  - Memos, 2002, 2004 (Box 175)
  - RCRA reports, undated (Box 176-177)
  - CY Today newsletters, undated (Box 178)
  - Photographs and slides, undated (Box 179-180)
  - Groundwater reports, 2004 (Box 181)
  - Environmental reports, 2003 (Box 182)
  - Phase 3 FSS reports, undated (Box 183)
  - Quality assurance reports, undated (Box 184-186)
  - NAC STS Safety analysis reports, undated (Box 187)
  - RCRA Field investigation report, undated (Box 188)
  - RCRA field investigation report, regulatory correspondence, undated, 2001 (Box 189)
  - Regulatory correspondence, 2001-2002 (Box 190)
  - Regulatory correspondence, 2003 (Box 191)
  - Regulatory correspondence, 2002-2003 (Box 192)
  - Regulatory correspondence, 2002 (Box 193)
  - Regulatory correspondence, 2001 (Box 194)